Finding Aid for the Ferdinando Paër Papers, 1807-1838
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Ferdinando Paër Papers, 1807-1838
Mus. Arc. 53
Paër, Ferdinando, 1771-1839
1 container (14 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains fourteen documents, including twelve letters from Paër to associates and friends and two documents showing his services rendered for the fiscal years 1811 and 1813.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from various antiquarians.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
The documents have been digitized. Links are provided to the digital versions along with transcriptions and English translations.
Biographical Note
Ferdinando Paër was born June 1 1771 in Parma, Italy. His father Giulio Pär (Ferdinando changed the spelling to Paër some time before 1810) was a trumpet and horn player in the Parma court orchestra. Paër studied music with Gaspare Ghiretti and Gian Francesco Fortunati (1746-1841).
Paër is most noted as a composer of fifty-five operas. He also composed numerous sacred vocal works, including cantatas, oratorios, and masses. His instrumental output included about ten symphonies and a small number of chamber works.
Paër spent the bulk of his career in Paris after moving there around 1807. Prior to that he served in various positions in Parma, Vienna, Prague, and Dresden. Paër was an influential musician in Paris, holding positions at the royal court and serving as director of the Théâtre Italien 1812-1818, 1819-1824, and 1826-1827. His most prominent student was Franz Liszt (1811-1886). Paër died in Paris May 3 1839.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains twelve letters from Paër to associates and friends, including composer Luigi Cherubini, music publisher and singer Isidore Consul, music publisher Giovanni Ricordi, the founder and first director of the Paris Conservatory Bernard Sarrette, and composer/pianist Pierre-Joseph-Guillaume Zimmermann. Also included are two documents showing his service for the royal court for the fiscal years 1811 and 1813.
Arrangement
The collection is chiefly arranged in chronological order, with newly acquired items beginning at Item 14.
Container List
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Carissimo amico" September 29, [1807-1810?], 1 manuscript leaf; Stamp on verso: "Autograph collection of Dr. Max Thorek, Chicago". (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Letter in Italian concerning the recipient's planned trip to Italy. Paër mentions providing letters for the recipient.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Monsieur Saret Directeur du Conservatoire Imperial de Musique" 28 February 1811, 1 folded manuscript leaf (2 pages); Recipient: Sarrette, Bernard, 1765-1858, founder of the Paris Conservatoire. At head of paper: "Service de S.M. l'Empereur et Roi. Le Directeur du Theâtre de la Cour et de la Musique Particuliere de S. M. I. et R. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Letter in French.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Monsieur Saret Directeur du Conservatoire Imperial de Musique" 28 March 1811, 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Sarrette, Bernard, 1765-1858, founder of the Paris Conservatoire. At head of paper: "Service de S.M. l'Empereur et Roi. Le Directeur du Theâtre de la Cour et de la Musique Particuliere de S. M. I. et R. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Exercice, 31 October 1811 musique de concerts de S. M. E., 1 manuscript leaf; "Maison de S. M. l'Empereur et Roi, Service du Grand Chambellan"--Manuscript caption. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Invoice for musical services rendered by Paër, with mention of M. Imbault (Jean-Jérôme Imbault, 1753-1832, French violinist and music publisher).
- Exercice, 15 June 1813 musique de concerts de S. M. E., 1 folded manuscript leaf (3 pages) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Invoice for services rendered by Paër for the court theaters, including work done by locksmiths and by set designer Jean-Baptiste Isabey.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Carissimo Console" 21 January, [1820?], 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Consul, Isidore, French singer at the Théâtre Italien and at the Royal Court. Consul was also active as a music publisher in Paris 1825-1853. Address for recipient on verso. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Letter in Italian in which Paër informs the Consul that he is sending a duet Consul will be singing with M. Levasseur (Nicholas Levasseur, 1791-1871, French bass).
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Mon Capitaine" 3 May, [1830?], 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Cherubini, Luigi, 1760-1842, Italian composer and theorist who lived and worked in Paris. Address for recipient on verso: Monsieur Cherubini, Capitaine du Corps d'harmonie ...". (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Letter in French concerning Paër's absence from Guard duty.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to [Signora Marchesa] 30 October 1832, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Letter in Italian.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Mon cher Monsieur Zimmerman" 5 November, [1834], 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Zimmerman, J. (Joseph), 1785-1853 (Pierre-Joseph-Guillaume Zimmermann), French composer and pianist who taught at the Paris Conservatoire from 1811-1853. On verso: address for recipient. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Letter in French in which Paër mentions an aria he composed with trumpet obbligato that had been performed by trumpeter David Bull [sic] (Joseph David Buhl, 1781-after 1828). Paër also mentions Isidore Consul, French singer and music publisher.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Mon cher Mons. Baillot" 1 March 1836, 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Baillot, Pierre Marie François de Sales, 1771-1842, French violinist and composer. At head of paper: "Liste Civile -- Musique du Roi". (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Letter in French in which Paër writes about composer and virtuoso pianist Sigismond Thalberg (1812-1871). Mention is also made of Auguste Franchomme (1808-1884), French composer and violoncellist and a trio by Viennese composer Joseph Mayseder (1789-1863).
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to Saverio Mercadante 27 March 1836, 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Mercadante, Saverio, 1795-1870, Italian composer, conductor, and teacher. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Letter in French inviting Mercadante and his wife to dinner. Mention also made of Spanish composer Mariano Obiols (1809-1888).
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Mademoiselle Stratton" 19 January 1837, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Letter in French informing the recipient that her lesson needs to be rescheduled.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Monsieur Leborne" 19 January 1838, 1 manuscript leaf; Recipient: Leborne, Aimé Ambroise Simon, 1797-1866, French composer (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Letter in French concerning preparation of parts for performance of Paër's opera, Olinde et Sophronie.
- Letter from Ferdinando Paër to "Sigr. Ricordi" 5 February 1828, 1 folded manuscript leaf; Recipient: Ricordi, Giovanni, -1853, founder of the music publishing firm Casa Ricordi. At head of paper: "Musique du Roi. Le Directeur de la Musique Particuliére du Roi, et de Madame la Duchesse de Berry, Membre de la Légion d'Honneur". (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Letter in Italian concerning a request for music composed by Niccolò Antonio Zingarelli and Giuseppe Nicolini.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Composers--France; Music--France--Paris--19th century; Paër, Ferdinando, 1771-1839--Correspondence
Genres
Correspondence
Associated Material
Bibliography
Castellani, Giuliano. Ferdinando Paer: Biografia, opere e documenti degli anni parigini. Bern: Peter Lang, 2008.
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
There are 166 scores by Ferdinando Paër in the Music Library, all cataloged in its online catalog, BISON. The scores are in manuscript and early editions, with many variant editions of the same works. An online inventory is also available.